<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sarahs sepulture, or A funerall sermon preached for the Right Honourable and vertuous lady, Dorothie Countesse of Northumberland, at Petworth in Sussex. By Richard Chambers Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Chambers, Richard, b. 1583.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107948</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843640</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843640</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8386</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18385)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8386)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1167:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sarahs sepulture, or A funerall sermon preached for the Right Honourable and vertuous lady, Dorothie Countesse of Northumberland, at Petworth in Sussex. By Richard Chambers Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Chambers, Richard, b. 1583.</author>
                  <author>R. H., fl. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 13 [i.e. 27], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld, for George Fairbeard, and are to bee sold at his shop, at the north entrance of the Royall-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: R.H.</note>
                  <note>P. 27 misnumbered 13.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Northumberland, Dorothy Percy, --  Countess of, d. 1619 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8386:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8386:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SARAHS</hi> SEPVLTVRE, OR A FVNERALL SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, preached for the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and vertuous Lady, <hi>DOROTHIE</hi> Counteſſe of NORTHVMBERLAND, at <hi>Petworth</hi> in SVSSEX.</p>
            <p>BY RICHARD CHAMBERS Doctor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The dying of friends is the cutting off a portion of our owne fleſh.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iuſti &amp; miſericordes homines ſunt fundamentum ſeculi.</hi>
               </l>
               <bibl>Dictum Hebraeorum veterum.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Eld,</hi> for <hi>George Fairbeard,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop, at the North entrance of the Royall-Exchange. 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8386:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8386:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader:</hi> As it is ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the husbandman, to behold the blaſting of his wiſhed wheat, while the cockle and darnell grow vp in his field: So it is no great comfort to the Chriſtian world to ſee the brambles of iniquity ouer-grow the whole Land, whilſt the Cedars of Lebanon are cut down: To ſee <hi>Cain</hi> liue, <hi>Abel</hi> die; <hi>Eſau</hi> hunt in the mountaines, <hi>Iſaac</hi> offered on the mountaine: <hi>Saul</hi> purſuing, <hi>Dauid</hi> purſued: and <hi>Diues</hi> to fare delicately euery day, whileſt <hi>Lazarus</hi> muſt lie at his doore full of ſores, this hath beene ſome trouble to the Seruants of God. If we knew the good the godly bring to the world, we would deſire they might long liue in it: for they bring a bleſsing whereſoeuer they come. <hi>Abraham</hi> by praier is profitable to <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck: Ioſeph</hi> by prouidence is beneficiall to <hi>Pharaoh: Dauid</hi> by valour is good to <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and <hi>Abigail</hi> that beautifull and bleſſed woman, withdrawes the ruine of <hi>Nabals</hi> family.</p>
            <p>Among many mirrors of modeſty in this world, this elect Lady was a true mirror. Had any cauſe to boaſt in the fleſh? ſhe more: Shee was deſcended of a Princely family, eſpouſed to one of the greateſt Peeres
<pb facs="tcp:8386:3"/>
in the Land, bleſſed with an hopefull ſeed, graced with all outward lineaments of beauty, and endowed with all inward ornaments of vertue: yet it pleaſed the Lord ſo to exerciſe her here, that albeit in her Sauiour ſhe found peace, yet in this world ſhe had many afflictions. By theſe was ſhe weaned from the loue of this world, and by theſe ſhe is now entred into the Kingdome of heauen. To the end ſhe might liue in ſome memory hereafter, the Author of this Sermon, her ſorrowfull ſeruant, did firſt preach, after pen, and of late ſent to me this enſuing diſcourſe, which being allowed by authority to be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to thy view, I cannot but commend it to thy rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: and whatſoeuer elſe thou ſhall learne by reading, I hope it will teach thee to contemne this world.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine and the Churches ſeruant in the Lord,</hi> R. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8386:3"/>
            <head>SARAHS <hi>ſepulture.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GENESIS 23.1.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> And Sarah was an hundred and ſeauen and twenty yeares old: Theſe were the yeares of the life of Sarah.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> And Sarah died in Kiriath-arba, the ſame is Hebron in the land of Canaan.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere beginneth the fift Section of the law called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chaije Sarah.</hi> Where we may ſee how holy <hi>Abraham</hi> in his old age<note n="a" place="margin">Paulus ab Eitzen. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> is tried with a new and a great domeſticall croſſe, <hi>viz.</hi> depriued of the crowne of his glory, <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.4. hath loſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gnezer</hi> his helpe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Samech</hi> his ſtaffe, prop and ſtay of comfort. Now this is written for our inſtruction and conſolation. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4.<note n="b" place="margin">Paulus ab Eitzen. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>Inſtruction, to teach vs that the children of God muſt not looke to liue at eaſe and quiet in this life. They muſt not prophecie of peace to themſelues, and that there ſhall be no leading into captiuity, and no complayning in their ſtreetes. They muſt not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8386:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
dreame that alwaies they ſhall be carried on Eagles wings, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.4. and that all the ſheaues in the ſhocke ſhall fall downe at theirs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.7. But their dreames muſt be of Willow trees by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Babel, Pſal.</hi> 137. 1. Of ſheaues thraſhed with an iron flaile,<note place="margin">Seneca Trag.</note> in a word, of afflictions &amp; croſſes. <hi>Non eſt ad aſtra mollis è terris via,</hi> The way to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen is not ſtrawed with flowers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. A Chriſtian muſt looke to be a daily croſſe bearer;<note place="margin">Stella de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temp. mundi.</note> For <hi>ad immortalitatem non niſi per aerumnas patet aditus;</hi> A Chriſtian muſt not thinke to walke alwayes in plaine and eaſie pathes.<note place="margin">Orig. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> Hom. <hi>5.</hi> ſup. Exod. <hi>14.</hi> fol. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliue iter eſt, quo tenditur ad virtutes, ſed aſcenditur, &amp; anguſtè ac difficulter aſcenditur.</hi> Hee muſt clime hard, it is all vp hill, the way lyeth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Exod. 14 1.</note> 
               <hi>inter Epauleum &amp; inter Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orig. ibid.</note> as the <hi>Sept.</hi> reade it, that is, by turretting and towring, turning and winding, as <hi>Origen</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it.<note place="margin">Crux vitae aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae prodromus.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is <hi>via arcta &amp; anguſta, Mat.</hi> 7.14. ſtraite and narrow; therefore no way for a Libertine to walke in. Thoſe whom God will haue to ſayle to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen muſt firſt be wafted a long by the ſuburbs of hell, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 116.3. And they whom the Lord intendeth ſhall arriue at the place of bliſſe, muſt firſt creepe along by weeping croſſe, <hi>Luke,</hi> 9.23. It is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble without afflictions to enter into Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<note place="margin">Wirth. de vita Chriſti lib. <hi>5.</hi> Cap. <hi>2,</hi> pag. <hi>324.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.38. <hi>Ad regnum coeleſte peruenitur, non niſi mundana infoelicitate, cruce &amp; afflictione: non honore, fed onere.</hi> In a word, neuer went any to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with drie eyes. The firſt man that euer dyed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8386:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
went to Heauen, but yet take this by the way,<note place="margin">The <hi>Thargum Ieruſalemy</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that the cauſe why <hi>Caine</hi> ſlew <hi>Abel</hi> was, becauſe holy <hi>Abel</hi> oppugned <hi>Caines</hi> helliſh and atheiſticall opinions, as that there was no world to come, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for good, no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for euill, &amp;c. 1 Iohn 3.12.</note> The firſt that euer went to Heauen dyed a Martyr, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, here we may take a good hint for Conſolation in the midſt of our greateſt miſeries and higheſt pitch of our tribulations, namely, That the deareſt ſeruants of God haue ſuffered no leſſe<note n="*" place="margin">Paulus ab Eitzen lib. <hi>1.</hi> in locum.</note>, but haue indured as great a ſtorme as we can doe. Take bleſſed <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the faithfull for an example, and ſee how the volume of Scripture ſetteth forth the prints of his piety and gracious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, as alſo deſcribeth at large his life, and the many occurrences, alterations, croſſes and afflictions, which hee ſuffered in his life; as to inſtance in ſome particulars. Firſt, he is conſtrained to forſake houſe and home, kindred and friends, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.1. Secondly, No ſooner is he come into that ſtrange land, but he is inforced away from thence by famine, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.10. Thirdly, In Aegypt wonderfully is hee perplexed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.12. whether he will ſaue his life, or hazard his wiues chaſtity. But what need I recken vp more? for whereſoeuer he went, he found neighbours out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly barbarous, which would not ſuffer him ſo much as to drinke water out of the Wels that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had digged with great labour, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.25. Wherefore let vs haue an eye to a better then this preſent life<note n="d" place="margin">Non eſt requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vbi quaeritis ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Quaerite quod quaeritis, ſed ibi non eſt vbi quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis. Beatam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam quaeritis in regione mortis: non eſt illic. Quomodo enim beata vitae, vbi nec vitae? Aug. Tom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Confeſ. cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note>? Happineſſe is not to be found here.</p>
            <p>But to ſhut vp my ſelfe within ſome liſts and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, this Chapter ſpreadeth it ſelfe into two braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. The one containeth the death of that Noble, Vertuous, and Religious Lady <hi>Sarah.</hi> The other,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8386:5"/>
the gracious behauiour of <hi>Abraham</hi> her Lord at her death: namely, <hi>Luctus,</hi> he mourneth for her: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a godly care for her funerall rites, and decent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terring of her corpes, verſ. 3.4. together with that which may ſeeme ſtrange, <hi>Emptio agri,</hi> The purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a place for buriall: for though he had as good a title and right thereto as any man hath to his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, it being conueighed vnto him by indenture, and confirmed by the broad ſeale of the Couenant Circumciſion, yet is this great Lord glad to crouch to the ſonnes of <hi>Cheth.</hi> Thirdly, there is ſpecified the buriall it ſelfe, verſ. 19.</p>
            <p>To looke backe vnto the firſt branch of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which in ſome ſort may not vnfitly be called <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rahs</hi> Epitaph, is contained theſe two things: Firſt, the time when ſhe died; ſecondly, the place where ſhe died. And beſides, the time and place whereof wee preſently will ſpeake, ſhee is honored with a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> double honour aboue all other women. Firſt, that ſhe is the onely woman whoſe whole age is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Scripture,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> autem ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e non fuiſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. Hebraeis ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diuinae Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> genealogias <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>exere mulierum, Damaſ, Orth: ſid: lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>15</hi> fol. <hi>163.</hi>
               </note> and whoſe number of yeares are recorded of God. In Scripture women are vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally excluded not onely from Genealogies, but alſo from Chronologies: That they liued is recorded, but how long they liued, and when they died is not ſpecified. Yet here the Lord by the pen of that man of God <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beda Tom: <hi>5.</hi> in Luc: lib. <hi>1</hi> pag: <hi>190:</hi>
               </note> doth ſet downe the length of <hi>Sarahs</hi> age: Firſt, becauſe ſhe was to bee the mother of all the faithfull: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6. as <hi>Eue</hi> was the mother of all liuing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. And therefore the great God of Heauen would haue ſome notes of eminency ſet
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8386:5"/>
vpon her aboue other women. Secondly, that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mankind may know that though they be the weaker ſexe, yet their life is no leſſe regarded of God then is the life of man, and that their death is as precious in his ſight, as is the death of man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.15. this caution by the way beeing obſerued: <hi>Si modo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſerint in fide, in dilectione, &amp; ſanctificatione cum ſobrietate;</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. <hi>If they continue in faith, and loue, and holineſſe with modeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond priuiledge is, that ſhee is the firſt for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> whoſe death mourning and weeping is mentioned, an other note of no ſmall honour: <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.9. And it is a great and fearefull iudgement, and ſigne of Gods wrath, to haue the buriall of an Aſſe, to haue none to lament, none to mourne for them, <hi>Ieremy</hi> 22.18.19.</p>
            <p>To come to the words themſelues, becauſe the yeares of <hi>Sarah</hi> are diſtinctly numbred, and the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes reade thus:<note place="margin">Lyra in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cum.</note> 
               <hi>And the liues of</hi> Sarah <hi>was an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, and twenty yeares, and ſeuen yeares:</hi> the Iewiſh Rabbins collect that here is commended her beauty and her chaſtity: <hi>viz.</hi> That ſhe was as faire at an hundred, as at twenty; and as chaſte at twenty, as at ſeauen. That <hi>Sarah</hi> was <hi>pulchra, &amp; caſta,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without impudency bee denied. <hi>Pulchra,</hi> well featured, well fauoured, the currant of Scripture is pregnant for it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.11. And the holy Ghoſt maketh her a figure of the new Teſtament, and of the heauenly Ieruſalem, the mother of vs all, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24.26. The ſpouſe of Chriſt is faire, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta,</hi> well nurtured, ſweet natured, pure and chaſt, is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8386:6"/>
no leſſe euident, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6. in that the Apoſtle ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth her forth for all women to behold, and as a glaſſe for them to looke into, and an example to follow in their liues and conuerſations: But neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe that which the Iewiſh Rabbins would ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not from the words warrantable, ſuch idle dreames affoord little or no edification. But from the words we ſafely may collect for our comfort and conſolation, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Lord doth number all our yeares, &amp; whether they be few or many he hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them down in his booke of remembrances: The Scripture ſheweth that the Lord doth very carefully take a reckning of our life; here <hi>Sarahs</hi> dayes are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely numbred. And <hi>Iob</hi> 14.5. mentioneth moneths and dayes, how that our dayes <hi>exactè praefiniti ſunt,</hi> are exactly determined, and the number of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths which man hath to liue, are in the Lords owne hand. Wherefore no good man need make any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but that the Lord hath a care of him, and that the thread of his life doth not depend vpon the skill of any <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> but on the good pleaſure of our God:<note n="a" place="margin">Chriſtianis eſt haec magna con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatio, ut ſciant, mortem non eſſe in tyrannorum vi, nec ullius creaturae manu poſita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neuè anxij ſint multum de morte, ſed velut pueri moriantur, quandò Domino placuerit. Luth. Tom. <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>253.</hi>
               </note> Our life is in his hand, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.15. Hee counteth our wandrings, which (God knoweth) are many, he putteth our teares into his bottle, and all our miſeries are firmely regiſtred, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.8.</p>
            <p>Concerning the time we may ſee the quality of it, <hi>Chaiiee,</hi> liues, there is intimated miſery; the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of it, for many a yeare, euen for the ſpace of an hundred twenty and ſeauen.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Chaiiee,</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. <hi>Chaiim,</hi> is tranſlated in Greek by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>life: Act.</hi> 2.28
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8386:6"/>
               <hi>Thou haſt made knowne vnto me</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the waies of life.</hi> And it is ſo named in the forme plural, <hi>Chaijee, liues,</hi> for diuers reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to note, that in the life of euery man are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> many operations, many changes and chances, many occurrences and alterations, riſings and fallings, eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bings and flowings: <hi>Mel &amp; fel,</hi> but more of the one then of the other. Mans dayes are euill dayes, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 47.9. Dayes full of labour, Man cannot vtter it, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.8. Becauſe euery day hath <hi>ſuam malitiam, Mat.</hi> 6.32. his griefe; and euery night <hi>ſuum terro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> his terror, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.5. in ſo much that the life of man is rather calamity then life. A good hint to put vs in memory of the fal in Paradiſe, and of the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion againſt Gods precept, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabo aerumnas tuas; I will greatly increaſe thy ſorrowes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. lib <hi>11</hi> Mor. cape.</note> From this <hi>Multiplicabo aerumnas tuas</hi> iſſued our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. For (as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>Quid in ſe habebit fortitudinis, qui natus eſt in infirmitatem? Quid aliud ex carne, quàm caro prouenire poteſt? Quid ex miſera matre aliud, quàm miſera creatura?</hi> Can good come out of euill, light out of darkneſſe, ſtrength out of weakneſſe? Can there come from a wofull mother ought ſauing a wofull creature?</p>
            <p>Secondly, to point backe vnto the Hiſtory going <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> before, which well eyed and carefully obſerued will ſhew that this good Lady led a carefull life all the dayes of her life. Firſt, if ſhe were the daughter of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> 
               <hi>Haran,</hi> which is the currant and receiued opinion of all the Iewes, then was ſhe an Orphan and fatherleſſe almoſt as ſoone as ſhe was borne: <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.27. No
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8386:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> ſooner borne but ſubiect to the croſſe. Secondly, when ſhe came to womans eſtate, then is ſhe likewiſe made ſubiect to affliction, ſhe is barren &amp; childleſſe, a great croſſe, yea in thoſe dayes reputed a curſe, that ſhe cannot bear <hi>Eues</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Iſh Iehouae,</hi> the man, the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Iacobs Shiloh, Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Meſſias, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45. our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Thirdly, conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to forſake her houſe and home, kindred and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> country; <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.1. and for the ſpace of 62. yeares to liue a Pilgrime. Fourthly, in this pilgrimage ſhe felt the ſmart of want and famine, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.10. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> Fiftly, in <hi>Aegypt Gen.</hi> 12.15. as alſo in <hi>Paleſtina, Gen.</hi> 20.4. ſhe was in hazzard of her honour, the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> woman Iewell, Chaſtitie. Sixtly, her Lord goeth to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> a dangerous war againſt foure mighty Monarches: <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.14. Seauenthly, ſhe was incumbred with domeſticall diſſentions, ouertopped by her owne ſeruant, no ſmall vexation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.14. Where by the way in a ſhort paſſage obſerue, that domeſticall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> diſſentions are not alwayes a curſe though euer a croſſe. Eightly, ſhee was not free from ſpirituall temptations, long did faith and frailty wraſtle and ſtriue, whether the God of heauen who is faithfull and true and cannot lye, were true of his word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the promiſed Seed. So that with <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhe might truely ſay: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.10. <hi>Optimum in vita la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor &amp; dolor. The beſt day ſhe ſaw dawne was full of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and ſorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all which learne this leſſon, and yee may write on the truth thereof; <hi>Nulla calamitas ſola, No
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8386:7"/>
miſery is alone:</hi> but (like the waues of the Sea) one followes in the neck of another: neuer let vs look for reſt in this miſerable life, till wee come to reſt with Chriſt Ieſus in the world to come.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point, becauſe that they who in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> their life ſee and feele many ſorrowes, are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to obſerue the time beſt, and (as it were) tell the houres thereof; <hi>Iob</hi> 7.2.3. Therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> doth not ſet down her yeares in groſſe, but draweth them out at length: <hi>q. d. Sarahs</hi> life and dayes were not ſo ſhort, that ſhe forgat them, but God did ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeably marke them forth with one miſery or another, that ſhe might eaſily count them on her fingers ends. That which hapned to <hi>Sarah</hi> is or may be likewiſe incident to all the godly: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. In the booke of <hi>Exodus</hi> chapter the 15. verſe 25. there is this paſſage, <hi>Ibi poſuit deus iuſtitias &amp; iudicia,</hi> Ther God made the Iſraelites an ordinance and a Law. <hi>Ibi, ubi amaritudo, ubi ſitis, &amp; quod eſt grauius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen Tom. Hom. <hi>7.</hi> fol.</note> 
               <hi>ſitis in abundantia aquarum, ibi poſuit Deus iuſtitias &amp; iudicia. Alius non erat locus dignior, aptior, vbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, quàm iſte, in quo amaritudo eſt.</hi> Where is this there, God made them an ordinance &amp; a Law? euen there, where was the bitter waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> there, where the people were like to periſh through thirſt, though there was water at will, and in great plenty: There God made them a Law, and gaue them ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, no fitter or more conuenient place could be found then it, where was the bitter waters of <hi>Marah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto of the quality of <hi>Sarahs</hi> dayes, now of the quantity &amp; continuance of the ſame namely, 127</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:8386:8"/>Although this noble and vertuous Lady endured many a ſharpe ſhower, yet neuertheleſſe the Lord continued the thread of her life for many a faire yeare: To make manifeſt to all ages and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to come, that the Lord preſerued her life in the midſt of death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. If euer any afflictions could haue haſtned the death of any, then might they haue haſtned hers, who for the ſpace of little leſſe then 90. yeares, was continually ſubiect to one calamity or another: In ſo much that it may ſeem the worlds wonder; how ſhe was able ſo long to endure. But God in whoſe right hand are length of dayes <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.16.<note place="margin">Mortem times, vitam perennem exoptas? in dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra ſua longitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem dierum habet: Qui vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit &amp; credit in me, non morietur in aeternu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ioh <hi>11.</hi> Immortalis eſt, mortem ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit: Immortali dextra, immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitatem porri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git: Baynus lib, <hi>1</hi> in Pro. Salom.</note> did preſerue her life in the midſt of thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries. Miſeries cannot ſhorten the dayes where the feare of the Lord is, but ſin may, <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.27. The feare of the Lord increaſeth the dayes, but the yeares of the wicked ſhall bee diminiſhed. And Iſraels Singer ſaith, <hi>Viri ſanguinum &amp; doloſi non dimidiabunt dies ſuos, Pſal.</hi> 55.24. Wicked men ſhall not liue out halfe their dayes.</p>
            <p>To conclude, though <hi>Sarahs</hi> life was repleniſhed with a world of woes, yet did it not want ſome ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular comforts. For this vertuous Lady liued after the birth of her ſonne <hi>Iſaac</hi> (as appeareth <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.17) the ſpace of 36. yeares. The Lord Gods good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was, that for ſome good ſpace ſhee might fol ce her ſelfe with that childe ſo greatly wiſhed, ſo long expected, and ſo often promiſed. Thus the good God of heauen ſuffereth not his ſeruants to depart out of this life without ſome eſpecial comfort, which ſweetneth and mitigateth all other ſorrowes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:8386:8"/>The currant of the Scriptures is plentifull to proue this point, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.11. <hi>In the multitude of the ſorrowes that were in my heart</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) thy comforts (Lord) haue refreſhed my ſoule.</hi> Shewing that as the world had a multitude of ſorrowes to aſſault <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſo God had a multitude of comforts to refreſh his heart. As our ſufferings abound, ſo conſolations abound, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Elias</hi> for a time mourned and was perſecuted, but at the laſt (beſides the comforts 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 19.6.7.18.) there came a charriot which freed him from <hi>Iezabels</hi> rage, 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.11.<note place="margin">Sperandum quod qui in vita mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; infernos tulerint, in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te mitius h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros. Luther Tom. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>75.</hi>
               </note> The man according to Gods owne heart (<hi>Dauid</hi> of whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſpake) had anguiſh and ſorrow, dangers and perils, many and mighty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.4.5. <hi>Funes mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> the cords or bands of death compaſſed him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; <hi>Dolores inferni,</hi> the ſorrowes of hell compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him: hee was inuironed with the pangs of hell and death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.3. yea and as it is in the 11 ver. of this <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. he breaketh forth into words little leſſe then of infidelity, accuſing holy <hi>Samuel</hi> the Lords Prophet of a lie, &amp; that he deceiued him in the promiſed kingdome of Iſrael. The God of comfort taketh not this his ſeruant <hi>Dauid</hi> out of this life, when his minde was not in quiet, when he was op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with inward and outward ſorrow,<note place="margin">Mortem iuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vocat pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, quoniam à mundi pugna li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berati, coeleſtem pa em coſequun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Hector Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in Iſay <hi>57.2.</hi>
               </note> but giues him a comfortable deliuerance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.6. O the infinite goodneſſe of a gracious God! Hitherto of the time, now of the place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Sarah died in Kiriath-arba, the ſame is Hebron the land of Canaan.] Sarahs</hi> daies &amp; yeres before were numbred, and found to be full of labour and ſorrow:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8386:9"/>
And now at <hi>Hebron</hi> thoſe dayes of miſery haue an end: now ſhe is at reſt from her manifold troubles, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14.13. now peace is come, and ſhee reſteth in the bed of peace, <hi>Iſay</hi> 57.2. <hi>ô praeclarum diem,</hi> ô bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and happy houre.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Horat. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Car. ad Lycinium Ode. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>Our Latine <hi>Pindarus</hi> could ſay, <hi>Non ſi malè nunc &amp; olim ſic erit,</hi> It is a ſtrange ſtorm that laſteth euer: <hi>Nocte pluit tota redeunt ſpectacula manè,</hi> which I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh by a better Poet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5. <hi>Weeping may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for a night, but ioy commeth in the morning. Many are the troubles of the Righteous, Pſal.</hi> 34.50. Theſe words, <hi>Many troubles,</hi> are able to amaze many a man; but what followeth? <hi>The Lord deliuereth out of all,</hi> This is able to comfort and raiſe vp any man. In the Goſpell of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> we haue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of our Sauiour, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.20. <hi>Verily, verily I ſay vnto you: Chriſti iuramentum, Chriſtianorum ſit fundamentum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> Chriſts oath and ſtrong aſſeueration, may be to chriſtians the ſtay and ſtaffe of conſolation. And what is Chriſts aſſeuera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? <hi>Ye ſhall weepe and lament, and the world ſhall reioyce, and yee ſhall ſorrow, but your ſorrow ſhall bee turned to ioy, Gen.</hi> 8.4. Long was righteous <hi>Noah</hi> toſſed with a tempeſt, but at the laſt, hee and his Arke reſted vpon the mountains of Ararat: from whence the ſweet Singer of Iſrael tooke the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of the Bibles briefe, a ſentence full of conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.22. <hi>Caſt thy burden vpon the LORD and hee ſhall nouriſh thee: Non dabit in aeternum fluctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem iusto,</hi> The iuſt ſhall not alwaies be floating, There is neuer a <hi>Go my people into Aegypt,</hi> but there
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8386:9"/>
is, <hi>Come againe my people out of Egypt.</hi> There is no leading of them into captiuity, but there is a bringing backe out of captiuity. There is not <hi>Enter Noah into the Arke,</hi> but there is, <hi>Come forth againe Noah out of the Arke. Non dabit in aeternum fluctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem iuſto.</hi> At Hebron the dayes of miſery haue an end.</p>
            <p>And to take a ſuruey of this <hi>Hebron.</hi> This City had three names: At the firſt it was called <hi>Mamree</hi> of the name of the firſt founder and builder of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.18. Afterwards it was called <hi>Kiriath-arba,</hi> of one <hi>Arba</hi> a great man among the <hi>Anakims,</hi> who repaired the ſame, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 14.14. <hi>and</hi> 15.14. Laſtly it was called Hebron of the nephew of faithfull <hi>Caleb,</hi> 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 2.4.2.</p>
            <p>It is moſt certaine that at this time it was the Metropolitan and Lady City of the whole land, hauing vnder it many other Cities, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 10.37. As it is ſaid of Sion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.3. So it may in ſome ſort be ſaid of Hebron, glorious things are ſpoken of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Antiquity, <hi>Num.</hi> 13.23. it was an ancient City, ſeauen yeares ancienter then <hi>Zoan</hi> in <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it was a Princely City, euen a manſion for a King, <hi>Io.</hi> 10.3.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it was for <hi>Calebs</hi> worthy ſeruice giuen to him for an inheritance, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 14.14.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it was appointed for one of the Cities of refuge, and giuen for the Leuites to dwell in, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 21.11.12.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, in it <hi>Dauid</hi> firſt reigned ouer Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.1.11.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8386:10"/>Sixtly, to this came the bleſſed Virgin the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt to viſit <hi>Elizabeth, Luke</hi> 1.39.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it became a place of buriall for many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy perſons, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.12. Here was buried <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his <hi>Sarah, Gen.</hi> 23.2. <hi>Iſaac</hi> and his <hi>Rebecca, Iacob</hi> and his <hi>Leah, Gen.</hi> 49.31. The firſt letters of the principall of all their names, who were buried in one graue, are contained in that one name of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And in this place ſome affirme was buried great <hi>Adam</hi> the firſt Father of vs all.<note place="margin">Hierom</note>
            </p>
            <p>The obſeruation which I collect is, that ſinne and ſinners ſtaine, pollute and defile all things, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.20. yea maketh each place where they come a hell,<note place="margin">Fulk. in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Ibi thronus Satanae, vbi pietas pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligata, impietas verò ſumma regnat;</hi> There is a hell, where grace and goodneſſe is ſhoued out, and where ſinne and iniquity beareth the ſway. So on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, whereſoeuer grace and goodneſſe is, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a good man treadeth he giueth a dignity and a kind of ſanctity vnto it, he imprinteth on it and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it a kinde of eminency, and inueſteth it with firme and conſtant ſtabilitie. To goe no further then my Text, <hi>Kiriath-arba</hi> is made excellent by <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> and from their time is made a ſanctuary and refuge, and a ſeat for a godly king to ſit vpon.</p>
            <p>What hath the ſpirit of God obſerued concerning the death of this worthy perſonage? Here is neuer a word of the diſeaſe whereof ſhe dyed: not a word of the laſt words which ſhe ſpake, which queſtionleſſe were comfortable, holy, and heauenly. But the holy
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8386:10"/>
Ghoſt windeth vp all in three or foure words, <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua eſt in Hebron,</hi> leauing the reſt to our further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p>Theſe words, <hi>Mortua eſt,</hi> ſhee died in Hebron wiſheth vs to meditate vpon the precedent hiſtory: It is well knowne to all ſuch as are conuerſant and exerciſed in the holy Story, the bleſſed Bible and booke of God; that the mother of the faithful, <hi>Sarah</hi> bare her ſonne <hi>Iſaac</hi> at <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> thirty ſeauen yeares before her death, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.17. compared with <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.2. As alſo that at <hi>Beerſheba, Abimelech</hi> made a league with <hi>Abraham,</hi> the tenure whereof was: That the one ſhould not hurt the other, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.23. Hereupon <hi>Abraham</hi> ſuppoſing hee ſhould ſet vp his ſtaffe, reſt for euer, and lay his bones, did there plant a groue, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.33.4. And when the Lord by eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall commandement ſent him to mount Moriah to offer his ſonne, for tryall of his faith and obedience, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.2. he returned backe to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> and there dwelt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.19. Yet for all this, <hi>Sarah</hi> dyeth not there, but dyeth at <hi>Hebron,</hi> certaine miles diſtant from it.</p>
            <p>It is very probable that after the death of <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech</hi> that good and moderate King, the inhabitants brake the league before made, &amp; troubled <hi>Abraham,</hi> in ſo much that now in his old age, when more then one foot was in the graue, this godly aged gray-hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man, with his aged wife, are conſtrained to ſeeke a new ſeate:<note place="margin">Luthar.</note> and in this their remouall religious <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> dyeth. Dyeth, I ſay,<note place="margin">Paulus ab Eit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen lib. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1</hi>
               </note> in abſence of her yoake-fellow <hi>Abraham,</hi> and happily without the preſence
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8386:11"/>
of her ſonne and other acquaintance: dyeth in a ſtrange place, and among ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chr. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> Hom. <hi>66.</hi> in Gen. <hi>48.</hi> Ne dicat quis miſerum in alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no ſolo vitam fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nientem, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cum qui inſolitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine ex h c vita decedit. Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enin ille dignus ut miſer dicatur, ſed qui in peccatis mortuus eſt, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſuper lectum, etiam ſi praeſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus amicis omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſpiritum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balet. Et ne mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi frigida illa verba, dicat ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis, Quod ille cane vilius eſt mortuus, nullo famil arium prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae &amp; funus ei contigerunt, &amp;c. Precioſa mors Sanctorum, Pſal. <hi>116.15.</hi> mors peccatorum peſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, Pſal <hi>34 21.</hi> At<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> etiam ſid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi ſuae moriatur &amp; muliere &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis praeſentibus. &amp;c.</note>The profitable vſes we are to make, are: Firſt, if the like happen to any other, that the Lord vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe them not to die in their own country, or among their owne neareſt and deareſt friends, wanting them to cloſe vp their dying eyes, and performe the duties and offices of loue, let it not be imputed as any ſigne of Gods heauy and fearfull wrath, for though friends be abſent, yet the beſt friends, God and his Chriſt, to the faithfull are euer preſent: And when all forſake, yet they neuer forſake, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.10. and heauen is no more remote from one place then from another.</p>
            <p>Againe the conſideration of that which hath bin deliuered, may be vnto all a continuall memoriall of ſin: It thruſt <hi>Adam</hi> our firſt parent out of Paradiſe, and made him a pilgrime, and hath made vs all liable vnto wauering and wandring. That the cauſe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction is ſin originall and actuall, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5.14. occaſioned and increaſed by meanes of the world, the diuell and the fleſh, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2.3. appeareth not onely by many places of the Scripture<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit:</hi> 26 14.15.16. <hi>Deut:</hi> 28.58.59. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 32 1.2.39.11: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30.</note>: But by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples, as of <hi>Adam</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.14 <hi>ad</hi> 20.</note>, of <hi>Ioab</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam</hi> 3.28.29.</note>, of <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.15:</note>, of <hi>Miriam</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Num:</hi> 12 10:</note>, of <hi>Gehezi</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2 <hi>Reg:</hi> 5 27:</note>, of <hi>Iehoram</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 21, 12:14:15.</note>, of <hi>Aſſa</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16:12:</note>, of the man ſicke of the palfie<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math:</hi> 9.2.</note>, as alſo of him that was ſicke thirty eight yeares lying at the poole <hi>Betheſda, Iohn</hi> 5.2.5.14. and many others.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, the conſideration of the premiſes may
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8386:11"/>
ſerue fitly to ſtirre vp in vs all a longing deſire of heauen, where all ioy is, euen riches of pleaſure for euermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8.9. ſeeing here wee haue no happineſſe, no reſt, no quietneſſe. Here is onely the valley of teares and weeping, elſe-where wee muſt looke for the happy place of reioycing, where there ſhall be no more death, neyther ſorrow, neither cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, neither ſhall there be any more paine, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame is Hebron in the Land of Canaan.]</hi> Where is Hebron ſituated? Not in Egypt, but in Canaan. Now Canaan is a type and ſhadow of the Kingdome of heauen, which <hi>Abraham</hi> and his <hi>Sarah</hi> longed and looked to enioy, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9.10. Moreouer at Salem a City of Canaan, <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> the Prieſt of the moſt high God, bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> reigned and ruled, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.18.19. This <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> was a figure of Chriſt the true King of peace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.2. Though <hi>Sarah</hi> dyed out of the ſight of her <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet ſhe dyed in the ſight, fauour and grace of her good God; and in the Land of peace, vnder the protection of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt the Prince of peace; who liued at Salem, preached at Salem, and dyed at Salem. So therefore this worthy and bleſſed Lady dyed there, and was buried there, where ſhe might reſt not far from the promiſed Seed, and might riſe againe with the promiſed Seed, <hi>Math.</hi> 27.53.</p>
            <p>But left (my beloued) the ſtreame of diſcourſe carrie me beyond the compaſſe of the time, and I ſhould tire out both my weake ſpirits, ſickly diſeaſed body, and your chriſtian patience, I will come briefly to ſome ſhort application concerning this preſent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8386:12"/>
dolefull occaſion, and ſigh out, rather then ſpeake out ſome few words: eſteeming my ſelfe in ſome ſort happy, the caſe thus ſtanding, that I haue the opportunity to ſhew <hi>Officia poſtremi muneris</hi> as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>de Verbis Apoſt.</hi> But as I wiſh all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour bounded within ſobriety, to my honorable Lord and his houſe, and ſo likewiſe to the name and bleſſed memory of my moſt honoured Lady and miſtriſſe, who was no ſmall glory to that houſe: So from my heart I wiſh, that in the performance of this laſt duty, ſhe might haue beene honoured with the paines of ſome graue godly <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> ſome powerfull preaching <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> or ſome golden ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> that as ſhee was honourable and honoured in her life, ſhe might haue had an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſon to haue honoured her death. O that it had beene the pleaſure of the Almightie, that time and place might ſo haue fitted, that the worthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God,<note place="margin">The B. of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note> who viſited her in her ſickneſſe, might alſo haue performed this laſt office of loue for her. The Lord grant vnto him and his, mercy at the great &amp; laſt day: Remember him, O my God, &amp; wipe not out his kindneſſe that he hath ſhewed on the houſe of God, &amp; to this Honorable Lady the ſeruant of God.</p>
            <p>As it was ſaid of <hi>Othniel</hi> a good Iudge in Iſrael, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3.11. That hee died, becauſe (ſaith the gloſſe) <hi>Indignus erat populus habere talem principem,</hi> Such a ſinfull and vnthankfull people were vnworthy to haue ſo worthy a prince. So may I truely ſay, we haue loſt a worthy peere,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.38. <hi>Dorothy.</hi>
               </note> the world was vnworthy of her: her nature was anſwereable to her name, giuen
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8386:12"/>
by God as a great gift vnto the world; (it is no ſmall bleſſing to be both honourable and holy, to be great and good) Taken away ſhe is for a great puniſhment eſpecially of her ſeruants,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 57.1.</note> who ſuruiue her in this world. Such was her conuerſation in this ſlippery and vnwoman-like age, wherein many fall and moſt doe ſlide, that I am of cleare opinion, that malice it ſelfe muſt needs acknowledge her to be no leſſe then an earthly angell, and a Phoenix of this world. Thouſand thouſands better know it then I am able to tell it: They are either blinde and cannot ſee, or too far tranſported with malice and will not ſee the many noble vertues of this noble Lady. She was <hi>pulchra, prudens, pudica, pia:</hi> ſhe was of comely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, of diſcreet and wiſe carriage, ſhe was loyall to her Lords bed, and louing to his friends: And for her piety, I know moſt certainely, that ſhee had more holineſſe inwardly, then ſhe euer ſhewed out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly: her diet was moderate, her apparell modeſt and onely needfull for her eſtate, comely it was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then coſtly: all yee of that ſexe reade <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.3.4.5. and when ye haue read it once, let me intreat you to reade it ouer againe, there you ſhall ſee what vertues the Apoſtle requireth at your hands, and if you deſire to haue an example to illuſtrate the Apoſtles doctrine, come hither and behold them here intombed: And in no one thing did ſhe more excell her ſelfe then in the religious and vertuous education of her noble children, ſeaſoning them to the great good I hope of this kingdome in the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of their yeares, with heauenly Religion. O
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8386:13"/>
daughters of Iſrael weepe:<note place="margin">Ambroſ: Tom. <hi>3.</hi> pag <hi>17.</hi> de obitu fratris Satyri.</note> 
               <hi>Ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> licet priuatum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, tamen fletus ſit publicus,</hi> Though for good cauſe the funerall &amp; ſolemnity of her buriall was priuate and vpon the night;<note place="margin">Lachrimae pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis indices, non illices ſunt doloris Amb. Tom. <hi>3.</hi> pag <hi>18</hi> de obitu fratris Satyri.</note> yet let your mourning be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and continue day and night. The Marble weepeth againſt a ſtorme, a ſtrange ſtorme is now lately fallen: ye haue loſt the glory of your ſexe; to ſpeake in a word, a vertuous Lady, whoſe price was far aboue pearles,<note place="margin">Her honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtianly the good rule of that golden Trumpeter, <hi>Chryſ. in Ioh.</hi> 19. did <hi>Tob.</hi> 14:10: honeſtly, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and nobly, performe <hi>offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um humanitatis, charitatis &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectionis,</hi> giuing a good preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to others to ſhew mercie to the dead, as alſo to the liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chryſ Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>Hom.</hi> 84. <hi>in Ioh:</hi> 19: <hi>pag:</hi> 137</note> a peaceable woman &amp; of a good heart, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 26.14. one in whoſe tongue was cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, meekneſſe and wholſome talke, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 36.23 This good gracious Lady, one of the daughters of the faithfull, was for all the world like <hi>Sarah</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the faithfull: For from the beginning of her life, to the end of her life ſubiect to the croſſe. I may wel and truly ſay, <hi>Ipſius animam pertranſiuit gladius:</hi> Many a ſharpe ſword of ſorrow pierced through her heart and ſoule. Now at her end without the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable preſence of her honorable Lord, without the comfortable preſence of her <hi>Iſaac,</hi> her ſonne of ioy and comfort, whom the great God of heauen make heire of all his parents vertues and graces, and (if it be his bleſſed will) turne from him all their miſeries and calamities, and make his name more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous then euer theirs was.</p>
            <p>But will ſome ſay, thus to be croſſed is to be cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: Curſed, a heauy word, and ſo to affirme were to condemne the generation of the iuſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.15. Yea and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt the Sauiour of the Iuſt, <hi>Iſay</hi> 53. For further anſwere hereunto, and for the rectifying of mens vnſetled iudgements, I intreat
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8386:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
you obſerue, that there are two things which doe not a little trouble very often not onely the weake, but euen the beſt in Gods ſchoole, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. verſes 2. and 13. The one is, <hi>Crucis duritia,</hi> the godlies great miſerie: the other is, <hi>Impiorum laetitia,</hi> the wickeds ſeeming exceſſiue felicity.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, <hi>Crucis duritia.</hi> The eſtate of the godly, is vſually harder then other mens. If any looke for chaſte <hi>Ioſeph</hi> where ſhall he finde him but in a priſon? If for vpright and iuſt <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.20.</note> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 2:8.</note> with a pot-ſheard vpon the dunghill? For godly <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 16.20.</note> at the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans gate full of ſores? For the mother of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, toſſed from poſt to pillar, wandring vp and downe. Yea, in a word, it is the portion of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36. <hi>Aeſtimati ſumus tanquam oves occiſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Wee are counted as ſheepe for the ſlaughter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the other, <hi>Impiorum laetitia.</hi> If miſery were equally the portion of euery man, then each might ſay, <hi>Et mea cum multis iuncta querela eſt:</hi> My com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, though it be but a poore comfort, my hap is no harder then other mens. But the wicked <hi>are not in trouble as other men, neyther are they plagued with other men, Pſal.</hi> 73.5. <hi>Baals</hi> prieſts, and the prieſts of the groue are full fed: they eate at <hi>Iezabels</hi> table, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.19. when as good godly <hi>Eliah</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet is glad to get his bread by begging, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 17.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Surgunt procellae ſtagni huius,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> The ſtormes of this world ariſe. <hi>Vides malos florere, bonos laborare;</hi> Thou ſeeſt the wicked liue in iollity and proſperity, the godly drooping vnder penury &amp; pouerty: Poore innocent <hi>Iſaac</hi> led to the ſlaughter,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8386:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
while ſcoffing <hi>Iſmael</hi> ſits at home: Good godly <hi>Iacob</hi> ſet to tend and keepe ſheepe, whiles my Lord <hi>Eſau</hi> rides on hunting. <hi>Tentatio eſt, fluctus eſt;</hi> A ſore try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, a billow able to beate a mans breath out of his body.<note place="margin">Aug: in Pſal. <hi>25.</hi> pag. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Et dicit anima tua, O Deus, Deus, haeccine est iuſtitia tua, vt mali floreant, boni laborent?</hi> And doth thy ſoule with ſobs and ſighes ſay; Is this, O good God, thy iuſt and indifferent carriage of buſineſſe? That bloudy <hi>Cain</hi> and his ſinfull race ſhould take the Tymbrell and the merry Harp, ſolace and reioyce themſelues in the ſound of the Organs, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 4.21. when if wee looke for <hi>Daniel,</hi> wee ſhall finde him in the Lyons denne: for <hi>Ieremiah</hi> in the dungeon: for <hi>Iſaiah</hi> tortured vpon the racke: for the Apoſtles of Chriſt in a common loathſome Goale: <hi>Acts</hi> 5.17. for the mother of the faithfull, liuing in a ſtrange land, and dying in a ſtrange land? <hi>Dicis Deo, Haeccine eſt iuſtitia tua? Et Deus tibi reſpondet, Haeccine eſt fides tua? Haeccine tibi promiſi, aut ad hoc Chriſtianus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus es, vt in ſeculo floreres?</hi> Saiſt thou to God, Is this thy iuſtice and righteouſneſſe? And God ſaith again to thee, Is this O man thy faith &amp; confidence? Was there euer any ſuch ſtipulation or promiſe, which paſſed betwixt thee and mee at the time when thou tookeſt that glorious name of Chriſtian vpon thee, that all ſhould outwardly goe well.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Proſper Epigran pag <hi>209.</hi>
                  </note>Nunquam bella bonis, nunquam diſcrimina deſunt,</l>
               <l>Et cum quo certet mens pia ſemper habet.</l>
               <l>Quae carnem oblectant, ſancto ſunt noxia cordi:</l>
               <l>Contra animi legem praelia corpus habet.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:8386:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Pulſant exterius diuerſis motibus hoſtes:</l>
               <l>Intus ciuile eſt, &amp; ſociale malum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>We muſt not in this world looke that our fleſh ſhall haue reſt, but wee muſt looke to be troubled on euery ſide, <hi>Fightings without and terrours within,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5.</p>
            <p>Since the fall of Adam no man paſſeth to Paradiſe, but by the burning Seraphins, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.24. No man to the land of Canaan, but by the bitter waters of Marah, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.23. No man to Ieruſalem but by mount Caluery and the vally of weeping.</p>
            <p>The tenure whereby we hold heauen is the Croſſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. and 10.38. That was the Indenture betwixt Chriſt and his Father, that hee ſhould not enter into heauen, but that hee muſt firſt ſuffer, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.26. <hi>O fooles, and ſlow of heart to beleeue all that the Prophets haue ſpoken; Ought not Chriſt to haue ſuffered theſe things, and to enter into his glory?</hi> And it is the indenture betwixt Chriſt and vs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Whoſoeuer will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus, muſt ſuffer afflictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The mouth that cannot lie, that faithfull and true witneſſe, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.14. ſaith, If any will follow me, <hi>tollat crucem ſuam,</hi> let him take vp his croſſe, <hi>ego meam, ille ſuam,</hi> I haue taken vp mine, and hee muſt take vp his, <hi>Luc.</hi> 9.23. A Chriſtian muſt be a daily Croſſe-bearer: For,<note place="margin">Aug: Tom. <hi>6.</hi> de Paſtoribus.</note> 
               <hi>exceptus à paſsione flagello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, exceptus à numero filiorum;</hi> This is good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique doctrine, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6. <hi>The Lord ſcourgeth euery ſonne that he receiueth.</hi> It is a ſhrewd ſigne
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8386:15"/>
that he ſhall neuer receiue the crowne, who did not firſt taſte of the croſſe. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.8.</p>
            <p>In the Booke of <hi>Iob</hi> there is made this inquiſion, <hi>Iob.</hi> 28.12.13. <hi>Sapientia verò ubi inuenitur? Et quit est locus intelligentiae?</hi> the anſwere is, <hi>Non invenitur in terra ſuaviter viventium,</hi> as the vulgar latine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: So may I ſay concerning Piety, the feare of God, grace and goodneſſe, where are they to bee found? <hi>Non in terra ſuaviter viventium,</hi> Not in the Land which liueth in pleaſure, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.5. If you find a land of good fellowes, if you ſeeke for grace and goodneſſe, you muſt ſeeke ſome where elſe, for you ſhall not finde them there. But to returne vnto this worthy Lady, though ſhe were <hi>afflicta,</hi> yet was ſhe not <hi>derelicta, Pſal.</hi> 37.26. She had her many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, Oliue plants about her table, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 128.3. not one but many dutifull children, children tractable to piety and goodneſſe, children free from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtaine of this ſinfull age. Moreouer ſhee died in good time for her ſelfe, though too ſoone for me and many moe:<note place="margin">Sibi maturè, aut mihi citò.</note> ſhe came to the graue in a good age: to the graue often before wiſhed, often before deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. Often haue I heard her vtter the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of theſe following verſes:
<q>
                  <l>Vita diu mihi poena fuit, me nulla voluptas</l>
                  <l>Incitat, ut cupiam longius eſſe ſuper.</l>
                  <l>Mors melior vita, certa mihi mente videtur,</l>
                  <l>Quae ridimit cunctis pectora feſſa malis.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But my ſpirits faile, my paſſions will not ſuffer me
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8386:15"/>
ſpeake, the fountaine is full, therefore well may it ouerflow: we therefore that doe remaine haue this for our comfort, and it is no ſmall comfort, that ſhe liued and died in a Land, where vnder a gracious Prince of peace the word of life is publiſhed: and in this vale of miſery ſhe tooke vp Chriſts croſſe, ſhe paſſed the burning Seraphins, therefore hath ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Paradiſe<note n="*" place="margin">Habent omnes animae cum de ſeculo exierint diverſas recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones ſuas, habent gaudium boni, &amp; mali tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. Aug. in Ioh: <hi>11.</hi> Tract. <hi>49.</hi> pag: <hi>442.</hi>
               </note>: ſhee did drinke many a deepe draught of the bitter waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> therefore ſhe hath ſet foote into the Land of promiſe the true <hi>Canaan:</hi> ſhe hath climbed vp mount <hi>Caluarie,</hi> and waded many a wet footſtep through the vallie of weeping, therefore ſhe is aſcended mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and come to the City of the liuing God, the Coeleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Hieruſalem, and to the company of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Angels, and to the Aſſembly and Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the firſt borne, and to God the Iudge of all, and to the Spirits of iuſt and perfect men, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. where with Chriſt Ieſus ſhe liueth for euermore<note n="a" place="margin">Fideles etiam defuncti, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra Chriſti ſunt: quamvis ergo cum ſuis corpori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nondu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſunt, iam tamen eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> animae regnant cum illo: Aug.</note>.</p>
            <p>But I muſt leaue thee, Noble Lady: thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to reſt in thy graue of peace vntill the great Reſurrection, when you ſhall receiue full bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<note n="b" place="margin">Quum verò ab hoc ſomno evigilabunt, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul omnes quod promiſſum eſt, accepturi ſunt. Promiſſa enim eſt fidelibus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio carnis, mortis conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, vita aeterna cum Angelis: Aug. Tom: <hi>9.</hi> Tract: <hi>49.</hi> in Euang. Ioh. pag. <hi>442.</hi>
               </note>, and thy Soule to bee with the God of peace, and with the bleſſed Angels, and all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the firſt borne, where you ſing the ſong of <hi>Moſes,</hi> a ſong of victory and thankſgiuing, <hi>Reu.</hi> 15.3.</p>
            <p>And as for you my Chriſtian auditorie, take this by the way, and thinke vpon it, This place and this Country is, <hi>Terra ſuaviter viventium,</hi> a Land that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8386:16"/>
liueth too much in pleaſure, too much giuen to the common ſinne of this age,<note place="margin">Hor epiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> ad Albium Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullum.</note> that is, too many are, <hi>Epicuri de grege porci:</hi> to engliſh it in the Apoſtles phraſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32. Beaſts of Epheſus giuen to eating and drinking<note n="c" place="margin">To remedy this great euill which hath bin the ruine of many of his Maieſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of their goods, and loſſe of their liues in theſe parts: I wiſh the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Iuſtices would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to giue eare to theſe my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts: Firſt, That no Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe be ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon the edge of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and in obſcure places, where Rogues, and Theeues may reſort. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, not to licence any in a village, when the Miniſter thereof and all the whole Pariſh ſhall think it vnfit. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not to licence any, who hath iuſtly ſtood for miſdemeanours excommunicated a yeare or two. Fourthly, when the abuſe ſhall grow ſo great, that poore women out of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of their ſoules ſhall craue ayde, that their husbands may not ſpend all at the pot, and they ſtatue, that then there be made ſome redreſſe. Laſtly, that painfull Preachers or other Officers may be heard, and not checked, when they iuſtly complain at your Benches againſt ſuch places as ſuffer drinking, carding and fighting vpon the Sabbath dayes in the time of Diuine Seruice. If theſe requeſts be iuſt and good, I requeſt you harken vnto them.</note>. Conſider that here lyeth a Saint, therefore bee not ſo groſſe ſinners: Here God hath erected the ſtandard of his Word to his people, <hi>Iſay</hi> 49.22. His banner is diſplayed, and whoſoeuer are guided hereby, to them appertaine peace and mercy, <hi>Galath.</hi> 6.16. Here the great Trumpe is blowne, <hi>Iſay</hi> 27.13. <hi>O foelicem popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum qui agnoſcit clangorem, Pſalm.</hi> 89.15. O bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the people that know the ioyfull ſound, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing eare vnto this voice, for they, O Lord, ſhall walke in the light of thy countenance, <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.23.</p>
            <p>And (I pray you) is not this his word or voice, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34. <hi>Take heed to your ſelues, leſt at any time your hearts bee oppreſſed with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But at this time I will preſſe this point no more, here I will abruptly end, and that portion of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which was lately my text for a Sermon, I will make now the concluſion of this my Sermon. <hi>Now
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8386:16"/>
the God of peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Ieſus, that great Shepheard of the Sheep, through the bloud of the euerlaſting Couenant, make you perfect in euery good worke to do his will, working in you that which is well pleaſing in his ſight, through Ieſus Chriſt, to whom be glory for euer and euer, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
